Guide to the Sarah Brown Ingersoll Cooper Papers, 1813-1921
Cooper, Sarah Brown Ingersoll Papers, 1813-1921
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Sarah Brown Ingersoll Cooper Papers 1813-1921
6543
Sarah Brown Ingersoll Cooper
13.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, diaries, newspaper clippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Personal material and material relating to Sarah B. Cooper's work in Bible Schools, Kindergartens, and Women's Organizations.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Sarah Brown Ingersoll was born on December 12, 1835 in Cazenovia, New York, the eldest in a family of three girls. She attended Cazenovia Seminary, where she met Halsey Fenimore Cooper, and Troy Female Seminary. Halsey and Sarah married in 1855 and moved to Chattanooga, Tennessee, where they worked together at a newspaper called The Advertiser, Halsey as the editor and Sarah as the assistant editor. They had two daughters: Harriet in 1856 and Mollie in 1861. The family fled the Civil War in 1861 and moved to Washington D.C., but returned south to Memphis in 1863. Mollie's death in 1864 cast Sarah into a deep depression and she became gravely ill. Sarah spent two years recuperating in St. Paul, Minnesota, but her health did not drastically improve until Halsey moved the family to San Francisco in 1869.
In San Francisco, Sarah taught a Bible Class at the Calvary Presbyterian Church which became hugely popular, and her class of seven students increased to hundreds within a few years. In 1879 Sarah founded the Jackson Street Kindergarten Association, later to be renamed The Golden Gate Kindergarten Association, and opened the first free kindergarten west of the Rocky Mountains in San Francisco. The family lived happily in San Francisco until 1879 when Halsey lost his job with the Internal Revenue Service. Sarah was heavily involved in many religious, educational, and social justice organizations but did not receive remuneration for any of these projects. The family experienced a serious financial strain and had difficulty covering their mortgage payments. In 1885 a group of the Coopers' friends secretly put together a fund to pay their mortgage in full and were planning to present it to the family as a Christmas present. Unfortunately, the friends' effort was in vain. Halsey could not live with the shame of not being able to provide for his family and tragically committed suicide on December 6, 1885. After a period of intense grieving, Sarah set out to clear Halsey's name. John Morton, Surveyor of the Internal Revenue Service, claimed in interviews that he had offered Halsey another position after removing him from his post as Deputy Surveyor. Sarah wrote and published a scathing denunciation entitled A Refutation, in which she included reprints of correspondence between John Morton and her late husband that effectively disproved John Morton's claims.
Sarah and Harriet continued with their philanthropic pursuits and Harriet quit her teaching job in order to act as her mother's personal secretary and dedicate more of her time to Kindergarten and Women's groups. Sarah was a tireless worker; it was unusual for her to rise much later than 5 o'clock in the morning. In addition to her Bible School and Kindergarten work, Sarah was also involved with Suffrage and Women's rights organizations and served as Treasurer for the General Federation of Women's Clubs. Harriet kept up with her mother's grueling pace for a few years before finally succumbing to exhaustion. Harriet had suffered from mild spells of melancholia throughout her life and these became more acute after the death of her father. Sarah was unwilling to institutionalize her only daughter and instead took it upon herself to care for her as best she could. Sarah was able to thwart Harriet's suicide attempts for a few months but Harriet ultimately succeeded in killing her mother and herself on December 11, 1896, the eve of Sarah's 60th birthday.
CHRONOLOGY
December 12, 1835 Sarah Ingersoll born in Cazenovia, New York
1849 Sarah teaches District summer school in Eagle Village, New York Begins Bible Class for the community
1850-1853 Sarah attends Cazenovia Seminary Meets Halsey Fenimore Cooper
1854 Sarah attends Troy Female Seminary of Emma Willard, studies Music and Foreign Language
1855 Works as a governess for the Schley family in Augusta, Georgia Sarah is permitted to teach scripture to slaves on Sunday afternoons
September 4, 1855 Marries Halsey Fenimore Cooper
1855 Moves to Chatanooga, Tennessee. Works as assistant editor for Halsey F. Cooper at The Advertiser
1856 Daughter Harriet (Hattie) born Sister Harriet (Hattie) marries Julius Skilton
1861 Sarah, Halsey, and Hattie flee north to Washington, D.C. Halsey works in Treasury Department in Internal Revenue Office Daughter Mollie born
1863 Sarah and her family return South to Memphis Sarah organizes Bible Class for Union Soldiers Sarah is president of Association for Relief of White Refugees
1864 Daughter Mollie dies
1864-1869 Sarah falls ill, travels around southern United States to find a more suitable climate
1866-1868 Sarah recuperates in St. Paul, Minnesota
1869 Sarah, Halsey, and Hattie move to San Francisco; Sarah's health markedly improves
1873 Halsey F. Cooper given job as Special Deputy Collector of Internal Revenue for district in San Francisco
June-October, 1875 Sarah and Hattie on cross-country trip
1879 Sarah Cooper starts Jackson Street Kindergarten Association Cooper School founded Halsey F. Cooper fired from Internal Revenue Service
1881 Heresy charge brought against Sarah Cooper by Deacon Roberts of the Calvary Presbyterian Church
1884 Jackson Street Kindergarten Association becomes Golden Gate Kindergarten Association
August 18, 1885 Sarah's sister Jennie dies
December 6, 1885 Halsey F. Cooper commits suicide
1886 Sarah writes A Refutation- a letter to John Morton, Surveyor of Internal Revenue Service, in defence of her husband
1886-1896 Sarah works extensively with Kindergartens, Women's Organizations, and her Bible Class.
1893 Harriet Cooper suffers from Melancholia and Exhaustion
1893 Sarah gives addresses at World's Columbian Exposition
1895-1896 Harriet Cooper's condition worsens
December 11, 1896 Sarah and Harriet Cooper die
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Personal material includes letters, Sarah and her daughter Harriet's diaries, calling cards, photographs, and daguerreotypes.
Included is correspondence of Ella Adams, Philip D. Armour, Rachel Foster Avery, Earl Barnes, Sophia L. Boardman, Nicholas E. Boyd, Lucy Brinkerhoff, Charles O. Browne, F.C. Clarke, Henry C. Dane, John Eaton, Nellie B. Eyster, Helen G. Fairchild, George T. Gaden, Minna V. Gaden, Caroline T. Haven, Phoebe Hearst, Ellen M. Henrotin, Robert G. Ingersoll, David Starr Jordan, Miranda W. Lux, Irena Ingersoll Rawlings, Emma B. Ryder, Caroline M. Severance, William E. Sheldon, Harriet Ingersoll Skilton, Charlotte Perkins Stetson (Gilman), Sarah A. Stewart, Ada van Pelt, E.G. Waite, and Joseph Warren.
Also includes material relevant to works and organizations that Sarah was involved in such as annual reports from Kindergarten Associations, lesson plans from Bible School classes, and programs from meetings of Women's Organizations.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cooper, Sarah Brown Ingersoll.; Addams, Jane, 1860-1935.; Anthony, Susan B.(Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Avery, Rachel Foster, 1858-1919.; Barton, Clara, 1821-1912.; Boardman, Sophia L.; Cooper, Harriet.; Dickinson, Mary Lowe.; Eaton, John.; Eyster, Nellie B.; Gaden, George T.; Gaden, Minna V.; Gilman, Charlotte Perkins, 1860-1935.; Hearst, Phoebe Apperton, 1842-1919.; Henrotin, Ellen M.; Ingersoll, Robert Green, 1833-1899.; Lux, Miranda W.; Rawlings, Irena Ingersoll.; Severance, Caroline M.; Sewall, May Wright, 1844-1920.; Sheldon, William E.; Skilton, Harriet Ingersoll.; Skilton family.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop,1828-1905.; Stanford, Leland,1824-1893.; Stewart, Sarah A.; Van Pelt, Ada.; Waite, E. G.; Warren, Joseph.; Willard, Emma, 1787-1870; Willard, Frances Elizabeth, 1839-1898.; Golden Gate Kindergarten Association of San Francisco.; General Federation of Women's Clubs; Hull House Association; World's Columbian Exposition(1893:Chicago, Ill.)
Subjects:
Depression, Mental.; Educators.; Kindergarten.; Presbyterian Church.; Social problems.; Social reformers.; Sunday schools.; Temperance.; Women Diaries.; Women social reformers.; Women Suffrage.
Places:
Cazenovia (N.Y.); Cazenovia Seminary (Cazenovia, N.Y.); Chattanooga (Tenn.); San Francisco (Calif.); Troy Female Seminary
Form and Genre:
Accounts.; Diaries.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
Frank A. Skilton papers, #1273. Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Julius A. Skilton papers, #1273. Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence and Personal Material, 1813-1921
General correspondence between Sarah Cooper and her family and friends as well as letters from Susan B. Anthony, Frances Willard, Anna Howard Shaw, and Robert G. Ingersoll. Also letters and material concerning Sarah Cooper's involvement in the Reverend Brown trial and her own Heresy Trial. Diaries of Sarah Cooper and her daughter Harriet and biographical sketches of Sarah.
Series II. Writings, 1844-1895
Manuscript of The Bankrupt's Daughter, a novel by Sarah Cooper; essays; articles; speeches.
Series III. Education, 1871-1906
Lessons from Sarah Cooper's Bible Classes; Annual Reports from the Golden Gate Kindergarten Association; essays on Kindergartens and Education by Sarah Cooper and others
Series IV. Women's Organizations, 1881-1898
Series V. Photographs and Daguerreotypes, 1850-1897
includes photographs and daguerreotypes of Sarah Cooper, her family, friends, kindergartens.
Series VI. Clippings, 1850-1899
Newspaper clippings by or related to Sarah Cooper.
Series VII. Miscellaneous
Miscellany
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence and Personal Material
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1813-1838 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1848-1851 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Jan. 1852-May1852 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 1852-Dec. 1852 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Jan. 1854-Aug. 1854 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1854-Dec. 1854 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: To Sarah from Halsey F. Cooper prior to marriage; 1855 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Jan. 1855-June 1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1855-Aug. 1855 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1855-Dec. 1855 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Jan. 1856-May 1856 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 1856-Dec. 1856 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letter from Civil War Prisoner of War to Sarah; Confederate Postage Stamps; 1862 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters of condolence after the death of Sarah's daughter Mollie and roses from her grave; 1864 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1866 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several newspaper clippings about Radical Republicans of the time; Aug. 1866 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1866 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several rejection letters from publishing companies for Sarah's manuscripts; Feb. 1868-June 1868 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several rejection letters from publishing companies for Sarah's manuscripts; July 1868-Dec. 1868 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Jan. 1871-June 1871 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter commending Sarah on one of her magazine articles and another letter requesting her to write an article for a magazine; July 1871-Dec. 1871 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Jan. 1875-June 1875 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1, 1875-July 15, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 16, 1875-July 22, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 23, 1875-July 31, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug. 1, 1875-Aug.7, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug.8, 1875-Aug. 12, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug. 13, 1875-Aug.21, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes clippings and letters about the possible suicide of Mr. Ralston, President of the Bank of California and about the closing of the bank; Aug.22, 1875-Aug.27, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug.28, 1875-Aug.31, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1, 1875-Sept.5, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept.6, 1875-Sept. 15, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 16, 1875-Sept.20, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept.21, 1875-Sept.26, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept.27, 1875-Sept.29, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Oct. 1875 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Nov. 1875-Dec. 1875 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter about driving the Chinese out of California; Jan. 1876-June 1876 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1876-Sept. 1876 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Oct. 1876-Dec. 1876 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter to Sarah from U.S. Commissioner of Education John Eaton about the removal of federal troops from the South and the end of Reconstruction; Jan. 1877-Mar. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Apr. 1877-May 1877 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 1877-July 1877 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug. 1877-Sept. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters from Chinese children in San Francisco to their teachers; Oct. 1877-Nov. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters from Chinese children in San Francisco to their teachers; Dec. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter concerning missionaries in Peking who translated the Old Testament into Chinese; letters from John Eaton about the possibility of Sarah teaching Home Economics to women in California; letters from John Eaton about the education reports of 1875 and 1876, Jan.-Feb. 1878 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Mar.-May, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 1878 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1878 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug. 1878-Sept. 1878 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Oct. 1878-Nov. 1878 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Dec. 1878 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Jan. 1879-Feb. 1879 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes correspondence between Sarah and the Internal Revenue Service regarding Halsey Cooper's position as General Deputy; includes letter notifying Halsey Cooper of his dismissal from his position in Internal Revenue Service; Mar. 1879 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter from F.C. Clarke concerning job prospects for Halsey Cooper and Sarah's Kindergarten work; Apr. 1879-May 1879 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters from F.C. Clarke regarding secret arrangements being made for Halsey Cooper's job appointment; June 1879 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1879 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug. 1879 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1879 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters from F.C. Clarke regarding Halsey Cooper's appointment; letters from John Eaton to Sarah about various projects in education; Oct.-Nov. 1879 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Dec. 1879 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from F.C. Clarke regarding the nomination of John Morton for the position of Collector of Internal Revenue; Jan. 1880 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Feb. 1880-Mar. 1880 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Apr. 1880-May 1880 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 1, 1880-June 15, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 16, 1880-June 30, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a certificate appointing Halsey Cooper as a Special Deputy Surveyor of Customs, July 1880-Sept. 1880 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Oct. 1880-Dec. 1880 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters in reference to the accusations of heresy made against Sarah; Jan. 1881-Mar. 1881 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Apr. 1881-June 1881 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1, 1881-July 18, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 19, 1881-July 31, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes the preamble and resolution regarding Sarah's heresy trial and the decision to allow her to continue teaching Bible classes; letters of support for Sarah during the trial; Aug. 1881 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1881 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters of support for Sarah during the heresy trial; Oct. 1881 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters of support for Sarah, a statement from John Eaton, and a letter from the New York Observer regarding her heresy trial; Nov. 1881-Dec. 1881 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from John Eaton; Jan. 1882-Apr. 1882 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from John Eaton; May 1882-June 1882 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from John Eaton; July 1882-Sept. 1882 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from John Eaton; Oct. 1882-Dec. 1882 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from John Eaton; Jan. 1883-Mar. 1883 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from John Eaton; Apr. 1883-May 1883 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 1, 1883-June 15, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, June 16, 1883-June 30, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1883 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Aug. 1883 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1883-Oct. 1883 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Nov. 1883-Dec. 1883 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes letters from John Eaton about the possibility of Sarah making a trip to the East in the summer; includes several letters from Emily Faithfull, a British feminist and publisher; Jan. 1884 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Feb. 1884 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter from Emily Faithfull about her visit to San Francisco; includes several letters from John Eaton about the passage of a bill which would establish common schools for American children of all races; Mar. 1884 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several letters from John Eaton about the passage of a bill which would establish common schools for American children of all races and about the possiblity of calling Sarah's association The Cooper Kindergarten Association; Apr. 1884 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, May 1884-June 1884 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1884-Aug. 1884 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Sept. 1884-Dec. 1884 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter from Halsey Cooper to the Governor in regards to the retention of his job through the change of administration; includes letters from Mr. Morton concerning his nomination of Mr. Brown to replace Mr. Cooper as Deputy Surveyor; Jan. 1885-Feb. 1885 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter from Halsey Cooper to President Grover Cleveland outlining his charges against Mr. Morton and a letter from Helen Fairchild regarding this letter; Mar. 1885-May 1885 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter from First Lady Elizabeth Cleveland regarding one of Sarah Cooper's papers on Kindergartens; includes a letter from John Eaton regarding a paper by Sarah presented at the Conference of Charities and Corrections; June 1885 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, July 1885 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes several sympathy letters after the death of Sarah's sister; Aug. 1885 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material: includes a letter from M.A. Cooper about the Cooper family and their relation to James Fenimore Cooper; Sept. 1885 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Oct. 1, 1885-Oct. 12, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Oct. 13, 1885-Oct.20, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence and Personal Material, Oct.21, 1885-Oct.31, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 36)